Guide to the William Dwight Whitney Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Papers of W. D. Whitney, (1839-1897)-1924; Series II
  - Notebooks and notes
    - "Catalogue of pressed specimens," kept jointly with Maria Whitney, 1847 May-1848 September (Box 50)
    - "Lists of Birds", 1847-1849 (Box 50)
    - Lecture notes from courses taken in Berlin and Tübingen, 1850-1853 (Box 50)
    - "Comparative Philology", 1873 (Box 50)
    - Linguistics (2 volumes), undated (Box 51)
    - Annotations, mostly in Sanskrit, on the backs of American Oriental Society announcement slips, undated (Box 51)
    - Linguistics, with some reprints, undated (Box 51)
    - Linguistics, with some drafts and printed matter, undated (Box 52)
    - Goethe's Wilhelm Tell and E.C.F. Krauss' Maria Stuart, undated (Box 52)
    - Memorandum book, 1849, undated (Box 52)
    - Miscellaneous, with some accounts and printed matter, 1881, 1892, undated (Box 52)
    - Bibliographical slips, undated (Box 52)
      General note
      Note: These slips were arranged in 5 bundles, each of which is now in a separate folder
  - Legal and financial papers
    - Account books, including one of "European Expenses", 1850 September-1855 April, 1856 November-1858 April (Box 53)
    - Accounts of stocks, bonds, and other investments, 1853 July (Box 53)
    - Accounts, 1865 September-1867 February (Box 53)
    - Accounts re: distribution of gift copies of his writings, Circa1871-1893 (Box 53)
    - Check registers
      - 1877 September - 1878 July (Box 53)
      - 1879 October - 1881 June (Box 53)
      - 1881 July - 1883 December (Box 53)
      - 1884 January - 1887 November (Box 53)
    - Income tax return, 1865 (Box 53)
    - Passport, 1856-1857 (Box 53)
  - Printed matter
    - Scrapbooks of clippings, including articles by and about Whitney, 1864-1893, n.d.
      See: Historical MSS Film No. 107
    - Reviews of Whitney's lectures and articles, 1859-1873 (Box 53)
    - Reviews of A Compendious German Grammar, 1870-1871,1874 (Box 53)
    - Reviews of Oriental and Linguistic Studies, 1872-1873 (Box 53)
    - Reviews of Index to and translation of Atharva-Veda, 1883, 1906 (Box 53)
    - Clippings about WDW's: controversy with Müller, 1875 -1876, 1901 (Box 53)
    - "Sham Indian Records", 1877 (Box 54)
    - Biographical notices, 1870-1891, 1924 (Box 54)
    - Obituaries, 1894-1895 (Box 54)
    - Mailings of various clubs and organizations, 1851-1894 (Box 54)
    - Copies of The Yale Gallinipper, 1846 February-March (Box 54)
    - Miscellaneous, 1848-1891, undated (Box 54)
    - Miscellaneous, 1851-1897 (Box 55)
    - Railway and insurance company stockholders' reports, 1864-1880 (Box 55)
  - Photographs and memorabilia
    - Photographs, undated (Box 55)
      See also: box 48 folder 12 (Diary, 1863)
      box 54 folder 65 ("Sham Indian Records")
    - Tickets of admission to lectures, etc., 1853-1856, 1876, undated (Box 55)
    - Wallets, undated (Box 55)
- Papers of Others, 1833, (1862-1912); Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Josiah D. Whitney (1819-1896)
    - "Report of a Geological Survey of the Lead Region of the Upper Mississippi": manuscript, 1862 (Box 56)
    - Miscellaneous clippings and printed matter, 1896-1909 (Box 56)
  - Maria Whitney: Diary and memorandum book, 1890 (Box 56)
  - Josiah D. Whitney (1878-1926) (attributed): ALS to "Dear Author", 1899 April 20 (Box 56)
  - Margaret Dwight Whitney: Molly Day (Thacher) Kazan: "Blocks," typescript of play, presented to Margaret D. Whitney, undated (Box 56)
  - Whitney family
    - Miscellaneous printed matter and memorabilia, 1833, 1869-1912, n.d (Box 56)
    - Hartford-New Haven Turnpike toll tickets, signed by James Hillhouse, undated (Box 56)
  - Unidentified
    - "Die Woche," MS parody of magazine, in German, 1912 May 30 (Box 56)
    - Miscellaneous clippings, 1872-1906, undated (Box 56)
  - Diplomas and certificates
    General
    Folio.
    - Edward Payson Whitney, 1854 (Box 57)
    - William D. Whitney, 1850-1893 (Box 57)